this is bigger pockets daily and i'm
your host tyler
if you're ready to learn about real
estate investing and you're short on
time
what do you say we jump right in
[Music]
complete guide to homeowners insurance
what's covered
what's not and how to find an agent by
whitney hutton
your adrenaline is pumping because you
just put your first real estate deal
under contract
now the real fun begins on your purchase
sale agreement
psa you see a long list of dates and
deadlines
one of them being property insurance
termination deadline
your job is to find a homeowner's policy
that meets a provision that goes
something like this
example is from a colorado psa
insurability
buyer has the right to review and object
to the availability
terms and conditions of and premium for
property insurance
property insurance buyer has the right
to terminate under section 25.1
on or before property insurance
termination deadline
based on any unsatisfactory provision of
the property insurance
in buyer's sole subjective discretion
now let's dive in what is homeowners
insurance
homeowners insurance is a form of
property insurance that covers losses
and damages to an individual house
along with assets in the home while
carrying this type of insurance in my
mind
is an investment must consider it as
your first line of asset protection
defense
if you are putting a loan on the
property
having homeowners insurance becomes a
requirement
it's important to understand what a
homeowner's insurance policy is
and how to read a basic declaration page
that way
you know what is covered under your
policy and what is not
additionally it's important to not
confuse homeowners insurance
with a home warranty or mortgage
insurance
the homeowner's policy will usually
cover interior damage
exterior damage loss or damage of
personal assets
liability coverage against accidents
that occur in the home
or on the property every policy has a
deductible
and a liability limit which will dictate
the amount of coverage the insured
you has should an event that causes loss
and or damages occur
how to get a homeowner's insurance
policy while securing a homeowners
insurance policy might be one of the
simpler tasks on your due diligence list
knowing how to get a great insurance
policy
is a little less intuitive here are the
steps to follow when sourcing a good
agent
in reviewing your declarations page one
find local insurance agents find an
insurance agent that underwrites
homeowners insurance policies in the
area
your property is located here are three
main sources you can use to find a good
insurance agent one ask other investors
who have property in the area where your
new prospect is located
two ask your realtor or lender if they
know of a rockstar agent
three check out referrals on
biggerpockets forums
pro tip while it may be tempting to shop
around to continually get the best rates
for each new acquisition
when you have found a great agent to
work with
think about concentrating your business
with them to save you time
and to keep your sanity 2.
interview agent or agents thoroughly
interview your potential agents and ask
them questions such as
how do you protect the home from a total
loss how do you protect your personal
property
what are your deductible options how is
inflation figured into property loss
over time
what is and what is not covered on the
standard homeowner's policy
how is home office equipment or computer
storage handled
especially in these post-covered times
what is your liability insurance limit
what is the process to file a claim what
can you expect from claim service
pro tip keep an excel spreadsheet so you
can compare apples to apples
while you may feel compelled to pick a
policy based on costs
also consider the customer service
aspect of the company you will be
dealing with
three get a quote if you are under
contract on a deal
have the agent prepare a quote on that
specific property
be prepared to provide details on said
property so you can get an accurate
quote
include age of the home age of the roof
and mechanicals
age and type of electrical on the
property known previous claims
on the property if you don't have a deal
yet pick a home that is very similar to
the one you are thinking of pursuing
and use that as an example pro tip
when you are first sourcing an agent
talk to at least three different people
and have a sample property you can have
them run for you
this way you can compare apples to
apples between all three agents
four review the declarations
review the declarations page and tweak
the quote based on your needs
here's a checklist of items to review
location of the property
make sure the correct property address
is listed there's nothing worse than
ensuring
the wrong property name of insured
make sure the correct people and or
entities are listed as the insured
on the property total premium your home
insurance premium is the amount you'll
pay
for your property's insurance protection
for a one year period and includes all
the coverage you've selected
coverage on your declarations page
you'll find a listing of the coverages
included on your homeowners insurance
be sure to review these carefully to
make sure you have
all the coverage you need to protect you
from life's uncertainties
residential fire all peril windstorm
coverage
you may need to add additional insurance
if you are in an inclement weather zone
tornadoes hurricanes
earthquakes etc or want water damage is
covered
liability coverage this provides you the
insured party with protection against
claims resulting from injuries and
damage to people or property
and covers both legal costs and any
payouts
should you the insured party be found
legally liable
personal injury coverage this is an
additional endorsement on your insurance
while bodily injury or personal
liability insurance covers things like
personal injury
insurance covers things like libel and
or slander
false arrest detention or imprisonment
malicious prosecution
wrongful eviction or wrongful entry
associated legal costs
medical expenses medical payments
coverage is the part of a home insurance
policy that covers you if a guest is
injured at your home
whether you're to blame or not generally
meant for small claims of one thousand
to five
thousand dollars loss of rents if this
is a rental property
you will want to know if you are covered
for loss or rents while the property is
vacant
and or occupied deductible
included with your insurance coverage is
in limits you'll also
see any applicable deductibles
deductibles are the amount you agree to
pay
out of your own pocket when you file an
insurance claim
discounts if you hold multiple policies
with the same agent
be sure to ask for a multiple policy
discount don't let the discount
tailwag the dog five notify your real
estate agent
when you have settled on an insurance
policy let your real estate agent know
this will fulfill the property insurance
termination deadline of your purchase
sales
agreement if you cannot find a suitable
insurance policy
make sure to notify your realtor so they
terminate the contract for you
within the deadline period six
submit documentation to lender provide
the declarations page to the lender to
fulfill the proof of insurability
requirement
buying the insurance when you know you
have the clear to close on the property
most lenders will pay the policy at
closing and escrow 6 to 12 months more
of insurance
payments to ensure the property is
properly covered
if you're not using lending you should
bind and pay your policy to take effect
on the closing day
things to watch out for while securing a
homeowner's insurance policy is
relatively straightforward process
beware that not all policies are the
same here are a few things to watch out
for
read the fine print carefully number one
policy exclusions be aware of policy
exclusions
common exclusions are earthquakes you
can view
earthquake hazard maps on the u.s
geological surveys website
to determine if you are in a hot spot
area natural disasters
these include such disasters as
hurricanes tsunamis and rainstorms
involving flooding or high winds you can
determine your flood risk by visiting
floodsmart.gov
landslides the u.s geological survey's
website has a map highlighting landslide
prone
areas number two anti-concurrent
causation clause
say what the anti-concurrent causation
acc clause is common and often
overlooked
this means if a structure is damaged by
two causes
such as wind and flood and one cause is
covered by insurance and one is not
an acc clause may limit your claim or
block it completely
basically it is a trap door built into
your policy
try to find a homeowner's policy without
an acc clause
if you can't think about buying an
add-on policy to fill
any gap in coverage number three
spikes in building costs and codes while
the lender will require you to carry a
policy that adequately covers the costs
to replace the home
when a natural disaster happens you may
find that materials cost and labor
spike very high i've seen this happen to
many friends where i live
after a devastating fire and then a few
short years later
a flood this is the basic economics of
supply and demand
additionally building codes may change
post-disaster
and add additional costs to the rebuild
conclusion to recap if you are using any
sort of lending
securing a homeowner's policy will most
likely be required
but what if you are purchasing all cash
the homeowner's policy
much like a health insurance policy is
designed to help you defer your personal
risk to the insurance company
so i still highly encourage it as it can
keep you from paying for high ticket
items
and to sleep even better at night i
would encourage you to set aside your
policy deductible in cash
that way you can always pay it when
disaster happens
like when your tenant's child drops a
handful of marbles down the kitchen sink
and it takes out the plumbing under your
house
thanks for checking out this episode of
bigger pockets daily
remember every thursday there's a new
episode of the bigger pockets real
estate podcast
and they drop an episode each sunday too
twice a week
sheesh slackers but seriously
check out brandon and david's show you
can search for it on your podcast app or
go to biggerpockets.com
podcast meanwhile i'll meet you
back here tomorrow
[Music]
you